Okay. And I am admitting everybody now.
And there we go. Good afternoon
everybody. Uh my name is Dominic Zerlo
and I'm with the Department of Health
and we are here to administratively
support uh this committee which is the
propagation committee. Uh, and the chair
is Chris Piscus. And so I will turn it
on over to Chris. And Chris, I'll bring
up the PowerPoint here. Uh, just a
moment.
>> Thank you. Well, Dominic's bringing up
the PowerPoint. As always, I like to
start these meetings off with just 30
seconds to
um create a container of compassion in a
world full of chaos. So, you all sit
with me in silence for that 30 seconds.
Thank you everyone.
All right, good afternoon. Welcome to
our third propagation committee.
[snorts] Um,
you all know who I am, an ambassador to
the Hero Arts Project that chair this
committee and I'm on the advisory board.
Uh today we're going to go over um
continue working on that propagation
outline. There's been some new language
changed and added and really want to
start kind of drilling down on that if
we can. This is always a loose agenda,
too. If we need to go off on a different
direction, I I'm more than willing to um
to go where we need to go to to solve
what we need to solve. So, uh after
that, we'll go into hopefully we have
sunset clause language from somebody. I
found Colorado's definition of a batch,
which we talked about last week, and if
other people have batch definitions, we
can go over those. Um, I added some
other definitions that might be helpful
um from Brett. And
um we have uh time for proposals and
other discussions.
So, with that said, please introduce
yourselves. When you introduce
yourselves, please let us know if you're
from New Mexico and any affiliations
that you have.
Remember, if you don't introduce
yourself, you are not um
not able to vote if we do end up voting
on something today. So, please please
take time to introduce yourselves.
>> Okay. First up, we have
>> Oh, go ahead. Sorry. Go ahead. Sorry. My
apologies.
>> That's quite all right.
Welcome back. Eric, your mic has been
enabled. Please unmute yourself when
you're ready to speak.
>> Hello. Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can.
>> My name is Eric Baka and I am a resident
of New Mexico and I don't have any
conflicts of interest and I'm return.
This is my third meeting. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Eric.
>> Greg, your mic has been enabled. Please
unmute yourself when you're ready to
speak.
[clears throat]
>> My name is Gregory Evans. I'm here as an
independent researcher. I live in Santa
Fe.
Um,
yeah.
Thank you, Greg.
Estan, your mic has been enabled. Please
unmute yourself when you're ready to
speak.
>> I've moved it. Hey everybody, good to
see you all again. This is uh Steon
Hernandez with the uh New Mexico
Micology Guild as well as New Mexico
Fungi. I'm a resident here in
Albuquerque, New Mexico. Um just wanted
to uh let you know, Chris, I am going to
be listening in today, but I may have to
come in and out a little bit.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you,
[clears throat] excuse me,
Priscilla, your mic has been enabled.
Please unmute yourself when you're ready
to speak.
>> My name is Priscilla Smith and I'm with
Crystal Clear Analytics which is a
humanist laboratory in some part.
>> Thank you Priscilla.
>> Can you restate where who you're with? I
I couldn't hear you.
>> I've enabled your mic once again.
Crystal clearar analytics.
>> Thank you.
>> Finally, I think we have Brenda with the
hand up.
Brenda, please. When you're ready,
>> everyone. Uh, thanks, Jorge. I'm Brenda
Burgard. I am uh uh chairing the um
education and training for the
psilocybin medical advisory board and
I'm here to um support uh the team here
in the advis in the advisory board and
um lend any comments or an ear to uh
what's being said here in the meeting
today. Thank you for having me, Chris.
Bye.
>> Fantastic. Thank you very much for that.
And we have some uh introductions in the
chat. I'll just for the sake of the uh
minutes uh repeat them. So Manuel says
uh hello my name is Manuel Jgo. I'm from
New Mexico. Thanks and happy to be here.
James Brown. Hello everyone. I'm James
Brown. Farm pharmacist I believe. Uh
solicy facilitator trained uh a New
Mexico US Navy uh veteran. Uh hello. My
name is Kayla. I'm from New Mexico. I am
a home health care provider. Gregory
Evans. Restate the company name please.
Oh, Matthew A. Uh, my name is Matthew
Armstrong. I'm from uh New Mexico. No
affiliations. Eric Barlow. I am
originally from Idaho, but I've lived in
Las Cusus for the past four years. This
is my second propagation meeting. I have
no affiliations.
Gregory uh says Patri uh Priscilla um is
that uh Crystal Crystal clear? I think
that was a question there. Um in any
case, finally, we have a comment there
from Dan Jennings. Hi, I'm Dan Jennings
on the board and chair of the research
and continuous improvement committee.
Thank you very much for that. And
finally, we have Brett Phelps with their
hand up. Brett, I've enabled your mic.
Please speak when ready.
>> All right. Good afternoon, everybody.
This is Brett Phelps. Um, I am an
attorney based out of Las Vegas, New
Mexico.
uh living in Morta and doing everything
I can to help promote the the program,
help establish it, and especially to
establish uh rural access for us folks
living living way outside of the uh the
major centers. So glad to be here.
Thanks.
>> Thank you very much for that. And
finally, Ben Edwards, I have enabled
your microphone. Please uh speak when
ready.
>> Yeah. Hi everybody. Um, my chat still
isn't working. It says it's only
available during the meeting and I
logged off and back on and it's still
saying that. Just FYI.
I am from New Mexico. I live in Tal and
I've been here most of my life uh about
50 years in New Mexico and I work in
soil micology land restoration and I've
been involved in in uh psilocybin
ceremonies for about 10 12 years and
doing other indigenous practices for
over 30 years. Thanks.
>> Thank you very much for that. And uh
finally we have uh Tay Davis. Hi my name
is Tay Davis. I'm in New Mexico. No
affiliations. So I believe that is
everyone Chris. So just to let you know.
>> Excellent. Thank you all for introducing
yourselves and thank you so much all of
you who um introduce yourself and didn't
for coming and participating and
supporting this. Um we need everybody to
make this program as best we can. So,
on another note, um Brett, you have you
ever considered uh you know, taking a
career up in radio after you're done
with your legal work.
Uh it's just
>> There we go. Can we bring go ahead and
bring up the the document um
the propagation outline? We'll start
digging back into this.
Give me just a moment to switch
documents.
Okay. Uh should be able to see the
document now. I'll increase the font
size. So for those who are waiting, it
usually takes a minute or two to switch
over into the uh how it displays. So if
you don't if you just see small tiny
text, give it just a moment or so.
>> Is this this is um
uh just a point here by Gregory. Uh I
may have a solution. He says, "For your
chat issue, Ben, if you are on desktop
and using the Teams app, leave the
meeting, close the app, go back uh to
your join link and instead of selecting
open app, decline that and open on web."
This solved the issue for me today. So,
just a little tip there maybe of use.
>> Uh Dominic, this was uh this wasn't the
document I was looking for. I was
looking for the propagation outline.
I think it's outside the folder in the
main page.
>> Yeah, give me just a moment. Um,
sorry if I open the wrong one.
>> I might call on Estabbon if you're still
here. I know you got to pop in and out.
>> Were you able to work on any language
for the sunset clause?
>> Hey there, Chris. Um, I have started up
on that. Unfortunately, I probably won't
have results for you until the next
meeting to review with everybody, but I
can also send them you to you probably
sometime next week.
>> Excellent.
>> Thank you.
>> There we go. Sorry about that, Chris. I
opened the wrong document. Just similar
names. So, [laughter]
>> no worries.
>> And just before we continue, may I just
insist that anyone who wishes to speak,
please do raise your hand. Um while uh
inputs in the chat are very helpful,
they may not completely be reflected in
the minutes. So if you wish to have uh
you know say something and your
microphone does work um please uh we
insist that uh it it would be very
helpful to us if uh you do uh raise a
hand and and can speak and if not please
do pop it in the chat. That's still uh
useful but it's just uh trying to ensure
that it's reflected in the minutes.
Thank you.
>> All right. Um, first thing, so I I think
I'm still encountering a lot of uh
contention around the authorized
species, and I just want to kind of um
go into this quickly or uh it doesn't
have to be quickly, but I want to
actually get a vote from people if we're
going to go with Cabinsus or if we're
going to try to push for more broad
um opening of species for this. Um and
the second thing I want to look at is
are these is this submission
uh requirements too stringent and I
think they should probably come to the
advisory board and not to the department
of health. Um, so first things first,
can I get a show of hands for who thinks
that we should limit
Oh, sorry. Go ahead,
>> Chris. Before you just jump into a vote,
just as a note on it is if it is not uh
limited just to cubensus, that second
part is not necessary. So the idea
behind that originally was because there
had been in other public comment that we
had gotten some individuals who had said
we should limit it simply to cubensus
others who have said it should be open
to other species. Um and so the idea was
is this is just the starting point on
that for the conversation. But if we had
done it with cubensus then it would
require that other species to be
considered down the road. But if it is
not limited to cubensus, that second
part is not needed. So just to make that
clear. So uh if if people are voting
that we limit to cubensus, then we would
need to think about that second part.
But if the vote is uh nothing regarding
cubensus, then uh that is okay. Um then
we would not need that secondary
portion. Dominic, just to quickly jump
in there. We have a question there by
Shane McDaniel and uh he asks, "What
does the bill say about species?"
>> Yeah, I'm pulling that up now so I can
just put it in.
As
>> far as I remember, I don't re remember
any specificity in the bill language
about
um specific species,
but uh I could be wrong. It's been a
while since I've read that. And I think
we have a comment from Gregory. What if
you want to go ahead and chime in?
>> Not really. I think I'm tired.
[clears throat] Um I'd love to see if we
can find a way to not even mention it.
If we could not regulate it until we
have to.
um
protect our like
context of
safety
um and harm reduction through analytics
and I believe the language is psilocybin
producing spe something like that I
can't yeah I have it close by but I
don't have it up
Um,
alternately if the language goes in
through the recommendation as cubensus,
um, I like keeping the research capacity
for broad in there, but I mean, let's do
less.
>> Thank you for that, Dominic. Your hand
is up.
>> Yeah, I just wanted to say that it it
does not state specifically. I wanted to
ensure that I didn't miss something with
it. Um, and so it does not state
specific. It just says found in certain
mushrooms.
>> Fantastic. Um, we have a hand raised by
Ben Edwards. Please Ben, your mic has
been enabled. Again, when ready.
>> Okay. Um, can we just leave it at
salosity is my first question. And then
I'd also like to get into uh the last
point of why are mycelio biomass
products prohibited? Um myelium is the
immune system of the mushroom and a lot
of people especially with inflammatory
issues going on can benefit from having
the mcelium uh as well as the fruit
body. So, I'd like to ask why that's
being limited and suggest that we just
uh put salosity in there.
>> Thank you for that. Uh next we have uh
Ben Edwards. Uh Ben, I have enabled your
microphone. Please begin when ready.
Oh. Um please lose your hand.
Okay. Well, uh if you put your hand up
again, I can defin certainly uh allow
for that. Um Dan Hus, uh Dan Houston,
sorry. Um I have enabled your mic.
Please begin when ready.
>> Hi there. Um Daniel Houston, uh Rose
City Laboratories, Portland, Oregon. Um
I my two cents on the uh um regulating
it just to psilocybin cubenzas
um I think is possibly a little bit of
an overkill. Um currently there is a
test that you can do for psilocybin
cuben
identify psilocybin cubenzas no other
species. So you can still work around
it. Um I feel it should be opened and
you guys should just concentrate on the
lab results. Um and then uh a little bit
about the mycelia. We've done a little
bit of testing on mycelia and um depends
on the uh the state or the uh time frame
that the mycelia is growing whether or
not there is any um psilocybin in it.
And different species will produce uh
different amounts of psilocybin
in the mycelia at different
amounts of time. I'm not sure if I'm
making any sense. So some mycelia will
not have any psilocybin until maybe a
week before it pins. Others may have
psilocybin long before that. That just
has to do with the sil uh my psyia. Um,
I did put my name or my contact in the
chat and some study or some studies
we've done. Feel free to reach out. You
guys should use these studies and
continue to build upon them. Um, I'm
just excited to be here. Thank you.
>> Thank you for that. Next is James Brown.
James, I've enabled your mic. Please
begin when ready.
>> Afternoon everyone. Chris, thank you so
much for chairing this. Um, my thought
on this, Chris, and everyone, is to keep
it open. I think the original intent of
the bill, and this is just me speaking,
was to have an open species. Um, I think
that the research again has been based
off of regulatory reasons, has been
restricted to just cubes. I think New
Mexico has an opportunity right now to
make a difference in our studies, in our
data, and open this up and let research
and analysis
drive those results. What I mean by that
is if we're just studying like in the
last committee solosen, then we go with
that and species to species, then that
would be something to look at. And
that's why I would like it to be open
and that's my suggestion is because if
we're just looking at the solosen
component of it then it you know species
to species will be different and but
again variability
with individuals matters and let's give
people a choice. So I'll leave it with
that Chris. Thank you.
>> Thank you very much for that. Next we
have Gregory Evans. Uh Gregory I have
enabled your microphone. Please begin
when ready. And I get a one two for
James Brown. One, two.
Um, exactly. Um, if we are going
medical, there is a there's a
[clears throat]
so a panelius should be
widely researched, but we have lesser
psychedelic psilocybin producing
species. Um, three to note are
Gymnopoulos, Inos and Plutus. Plutus is
rare in NASA is where we discovered
arogenessence.
If we are looking at getting into real
research for medical efficacy of minor
alkyoids and what these mushrooms can do
for people besides making them trip
in is definitely something that should
be looked at. The other thing I just
wanted to mention,
the only reason this whole thing came up
in Oregon around constraining species
was because Oregon is an environment
where
[clears throat]
philosophy, subarageness, and its
ancestors thrive. Subarogenessence
is the kind of origin species that
branched out over millennia and spread
around the world and have things like
cyanessence, aleni,
um, stunzi, etc., etc.
Those have been associated with a
phenomenon called woodlovers paralysis.
That is something that needs to be
studied. But the reason it's an issue in
Oregon is cuz every fall into the winter
you can go collect trash bags and those
were there was a risk of those ending up
in the market. That's not a risk here.
It's not something that we need to
protect against. We can't receive
mushrooms from out of state. Believe me,
I've tried to grow as a outdoors here
and it does not work. I know one person
that has and it produces about like a
half a gram. It's just not an issue. So,
anyways, back to the let's leave it
blank preference.
>> Thank you very much for that. Um, and
just before I get to you, Gregory, uh,
just some comments in the chat. Um,
Shane McDaniel states, uh, I agree. If
the bill states anything, uh, any voting
or decisions we make are mute? Estavan
says, beyond cultivation/ facilitator
liability, what risks are associated
with additional species? Does opening
the program up to more species delay or
adversely affect the program rollout or
license requirements? Eric Barker says,
"Do not restrict species." Michelle, so
many beneficial species ashamed to limit
so early in the process. And uh those
are the main points. Uh just repeating
those points essentially onwards and
that seem to be all of them. So back to
you.
Um,
I would like to go back to Estabbon's
comment. Beyond cultivator facilitator
liability, what risks are associated
with additional species? And thank you,
Greg, for bringing up wood lovers
paralysis
and um you know, kind of the thought
process that went into Oregon approving
u cubensus as their uh
as their primary medicine. Um but we we
don't face the same problems they do
there. So, I would like to open it up
for anybody who can think of any other
risks associated with additional species
at this time if they can bring those to
the table.
We have Matthew there. Um, Matthew, I've
enabled your mic. Please begin when
ready.
Matthew, I uh just to let you know to
unmute uh on the top right of your
screen, you should see a mic. You have
to click that to unmute. So, I've
enabled your mic, but you have to
manually unmute.
Right. It seems that we're having a few
technical issues there with with the
self. Matthew, um, in the meantime, um,
as we're figuring that out, uh, James
Brown, you have your hand up. Uh, your
mic is enabled. Please begin when ready.
>> Chris, a couple of other species that
are out there right now. Uh, one is
currently being used in Arizona. There
are clinical trials. Um, and the lady
out there who's a amazing uh she has
been using and I'm not sure if Dr. Leman
is using the same uh species, but that
would be something to look at. Chris
would ask Dr. Leman um and ask him what
species he's currently using in his
study. And then I I believe I know the
name, but I think it's called penis
envy, but I just don't like saying that
over the thing. But um you know,
something like that might be considered
uh safe and effective. Um but it is
being studied and it has shown clinical
research of safety in in that in that
species.
>> Thank you very much for that. Um
Matthew, uh just to come back to
yourself, I know you have your hand up
there. Uh let's give it another go. Um
if you're still struggling, your mic is
enabled. Um if it doesn't work out, jump
off the call and jump back in.
Alternatively, you can dial in. Um and
that and unmute on the dial in. I
believe you press star 9 if I'm correct
Dominic is that is that
>> so Ishmael I believe Matthew is joining
in right now on the phone
>> fantastic
>> um so Matthew I do believe that is you
to unmute go ahead and press star six uh
and uh you should be able to speak
>> uh yes hello
>> uh there we go we can hear you Matthew
go ahead
>> yeah so I You know, I've been observing
more than I've been talking and I would
just wanted to point out the dangerous
of introducing other mushrooms such as
like fly argaras. Now, this mushroom
does have a tripping abilities to it,
but what I'm afraid is that we're going
to get this neurochemical mushroom that
doesn't do the same as psychedelic
mushrooms. Instead, it releases like a
poisonous toxin from what I understand.
So, and then there was this huge thing
for a little while. I know there was
these swoomy bars that went around that
this fly argaras mushroom in it and
people were getting sick and so well I
know we all want azure and can mushrooms
added. I think that right now we have to
go with what's safe, what we know was in
the bill and that's why we should stick
to the cubanas in my opinion. I yield.
Thank you very much for that. Um,
finally we have Dan Houston. Uh, Dan,
your mic is enabled. So, whenever you're
ready, please begin.
>> Hi again from here from Roh Oregon. Um,
I just wanted to touch bases the fly
garrison is actually does not contain
any psilocybin. So, as long as the rules
talk about psilocybin containing
mushrooms, I think that it should be
open and and broad. Um, and then
somebody else mentioned uh the the
strain pen penis envy. The penis envy is
actually a uh cubenza strain and it is
widely used um here in Oregon for the
organ market. Um the the growers will in
my opinion have uh end up doing what
they do here in Oregon is try to end up
well they were trying to figure out the
what mushroom would produce the uniform
size and shape because we do whole but
you guys are going with homogenize only.
So um yeah, as long as it can says just
uh psilocybin containing mushrooms, it
will get rid of all the other
opportunities of other poisonous
mushrooms.
Um just my two cents. Sorry.
>> No apologies required.
>> Yeah, I appreciate your your two cents
for sure. And it is the the PE cultivvar
a problem, Dominic, as far as language?
Do we need to remind people to to stay
away from that? you know, uh I'm
actually not sure if they will
considering it as an actual body part.
Um but we will run it by I would just
request just uh to ensure that we don't
have additional delays in our being able
to post vid uh the uh the recordings if
people do just refer to it through its
initials just to be on the safe side
regarding that. I think this one we're
okay with. It's the other one that was a
problem, JMF. So, [laughter]
but I think this one we're all right.
All right. Thank you. Um, excellent.
Okay. So, uh, I think we've addressed
the only concern that has come up. So,
now I'd like to let's take a vote. Who
wants to push for a broad opening of all
psilocybin containing mushrooms?
Raise your hands, please.
At present we have 15 hands raised
>> which is more than the number of
attendees. So Chris that does pass. So
we will take that out. Uh and again as
mentioned that means that the rest of
this goes. The only other question then
would be with regard to the whole
mushroom. Uh, as far as that aspect, uh,
wow, that's an amazing victory,
everybody. I'm I'm like super happy that
we did that.
>> Um, see if we get it passed through the
next two two layers of that. Yes, go
ahead,
>> Chris. I was just going to say if people
who have their hands raised, please
lower your hands at this time. Um, we'll
start lowering them here in just a
moment if you're not able to or are not
sure how. Uh we just want to make sure
we don't miss public comment because
people's hands are still raised. Um so
there we go. Okay.
>> And just as a um I guess more of a
gesture at this point, I would like to
open it up to anybody to note their
opposition in the record. So if you
oppose that decision, please raise your
hand at this time.
But the record show that Matthew has
opposed
>> Matthew A has opposed that decision. So,
thank you, Matthew.
>> All right, we I lost my uh
>> Yeah, I had to take it off to put track
changes on. I'm bringing it back up
right now, Chris. Give me just a moment.
>> Y I just I didn't want to interrupt you
while you were talking.
>> [laughter]
>> to just say oops technical uh well
logistical item. Um okay,
next uh next up whole mushroom fruing
bodies. This is something I've talked
about before. Could be wrong. Uh let's
open it up to comment on for or against
using the whole mushroom only and
whether we should use myelio biomass
products.
Gregory Evans, you raised your hands. Go
ahead.
[clears throat]
>> I would say that there's no risk in
using myial biomass products other than
the concept of snake oil. our good
friend um and micologist
uh
I'm spacing dude's name
uses a lot of like lion's mane biomass
or like myial miciliated grains in
commonly distributed
products for like lion's mane and that's
a very common thing I don't think that
the market will push for any myiliated
biomass products
in the space of psychedelic use. I think
it doesn't matter if you leave it in
there. I don't think it really
has an effect. Um,
but if it's there to protect against
something, I'd love to hear what that
is. I just don't Nobody's going to do
it. Unless you are, I'd love to hear
your reasoning behind that.
We have a hand raised there by Adrian.
Please go ahead. I've enabled your mic.
>> The mic.
>> Uh, thank you. Uh, yeah. I just want to
say about using mycelium um, biomass. It
would depend on the substrate because if
you've got cultivators using manure or
compost as their substrate, um no one's
really going to want to eat or consume
the manure um from that, you know, from
that biomass. Uh otherwise, if you're
just using CVG like core, vermiculite,
and gypsum, there might not be an issue
in in consuming that. Um the only issue
here would be the the cultivators that
choose to use manure. Uh, thank you.
>> Thank you for that. Um, next we have uh
Gregory Evans. Gregory, your mic is
enabled.
>> Just put sanity on that. Um, and I could
add this to the glossery,
but myated biomass refers to myated
grains. Nobody takes bulk substrate and
grinds that up. the way you produce
myiliated
a myceliated biomass product as listed
by the FDA on the back of mushrooms that
you buy in the store that the
terminology for that refers to grains
that have been fully colonized.
That's it. So wheat,
my brain's not working. Somebody else.
But anyways, the grains that we use to
create spawn, they grind those up.
They're not mixing. They're not fruiting
them and then grinding it all together.
Like, so, so there is no concern about
grinding up horse poo. Also, if you did
grind up substrate that was horoo, it
would be very, very clean horse poo.
Technically, probably good for you.
>> Thank you for that. Next we have Dan
Houston. Dan, your mic is enabled.
>> Yeah. So, uh, we've seen people, uh,
take the, uh, blocks and actually do
extract extractions with it and all of
that. And I agree it it it should be
allowed to be used, but there definitely
needs to be some um, guard rails put
into place with uh, what can or cannot
be used as mycelia
for the substrate. And the other thing
is is yes, it should be done with grains
and stuff like that. And we here in
Oregon, we've had people get sick off of
mushrooms that uh had they they got
[snorts]
and that was because of a
crosscontamination the myeliaing body
touching it and then harvesting the
mushrooms. So think about you know
gluten and stuff like that that can be
crosscontaminated.
Thank you for sharing. Next we have Ben
Edwards. Ben, your mic is enabled.
So I I know of a couple of anecdotal
cases where people with inflammatory
diseases have had outbursts from doing
uh regular fruit bodies. And so in
addition to it, taking some mycelium in
corn or oat or something else has helped
them because again the mcelium that's
the immune system of of the mushroom.
The fruit body is super ephemeral. It
comes and goes in a few days. Uh but the
mcelium is really it it can
counterbalance some of the inflammatory
stuff is what I've seen. Um, you can
also do an iodine test to make sure that
the substrate is is adequately
uh dissolved by the mcelium and not high
in in sugars. And then yeah, you have to
test it like any kind of supplement as
far as crosscontamination goes. Um, I I
just share those points not to try to
develop a whole other protocol, but as
reasons not to exclude
Okay. So, from what I'm hearing,
we should allow myial products, but
there may be some issues in which
products we allow, how extractions can
be done, and maybe there might be
further testing
needed on those products. Is that an
accurate reflection of uh what I just
heard from everyone?
>> Gregory Evans, your hand is raised. Uh
your mic is enabled. Please begin.
>> I think my take is that we don't
regulate it, but as I wrote in the chat
to put on the record,
myated grains would qualify as a food
product.
I think that there is enough of a
distinction between mushroom fruit and
bardies that we passed in our
understanding of what is acceptable in
this program iteratively.
I think my siliated grains would be more
of a fruit food product. So I think it
becomes moot at that point.
>> Dominic, how do you interpret that?
Would that be
>> Yeah. thoughts
>> food products and then it would be more
stringent testing on on all of that.
>> Well, we don't have food, right?
>> We do as a processing if anything that's
processed into further than just
homogenized ground mushroom is going to
need to be um
it going to have to go through food
processing rules,
>> right? And that actually creates an
entire other level of regulatory uh
aspects that are not even with the DO.
Um and so that was a part of the idea
behind uh the some of the comments
originally with excluding the biomass.
Um and um
the issue as far as testing is remember
every test that gets added means that
there is more of a cost on it. And so
the question that I would have is
because several people here in this
conversation have said well we would
have to add these additional tests. So
which would be bet would be better from
a balancing standpoint of adding in the
additional tests versus uh excluding the
mycelial biomass. And that would be one
of the questions that I would have and
again remember this is part of the
conversation and at least as far as the
department is concerned what we're
really doing is we want to hear what's
happening with the conversation the
recommendations being made the reasons
behind it so that this committee and
then the board can make those final
recommendations. So those are all things
to think about and cost is and has been
brought up by many of the individuals on
this call and on quite a few of the
others as being a very important aspect
of it and I would agree with that. And
so is this something and maybe Dan
Houston could speak to the cost of doing
some of those additional tests that
would be needed. Um you know is that
something that we would want to do in
the initial stages of the program? And
remember, if we find that we need to
pivot with the program, regulations are
not set in stone. We do change them and
we do anticipate within the first year
to two years having and needing to
change them and modify them as the
program develops and we discover some
things that work, some things that
don't. And no matter how careful we are,
we're going to miss some things. So,
just always remember that aspect as
well.
>> Thank you for that, Dominic. We have a
uh hand raised by Shane McDaniel. Shane,
your mic is enabled. Please uh begin
when ready.
>> Um yeah, I may have missed something
here. Um I heard Dan say something
earlier about um New Mexico's not
allowing
um
fruiting bodies
to be used. Is did I misunderstood that?
He said something about only homogenized
product.
>> Yeah. So Shane, we have been talking
about the fact that from a testing
standpoint, because it is a medical
program, that the products are going to
have to be homogenized um in order to
ensure consistency going across the
board and to ensure that the testing can
occur. Otherwise, all of the different
uh what is ended up grown will end up
needing to be tested. Now again that
doesn't mean down the road that there
won't be other methodologies but in the
initial stages it will need to be
homogenized.
>> All right.
>> Well that was definitely a conversation
killer. Sorry everyone.
[laughter]
>> We have a hand raised there by Gregory
Evans. Gregory your mic is enabled.
It can always depend on me for
conversation.
Um, I'm like I'm with it. Like I think
your perspective there like
flips my perspective to just leave it in
there and then it becomes a non-issue
down the road and it doesn't make that
other aspect more complicated. I think
it's I think I would vote leave it in at
this point.
based on that.
>> All right, I think uh we'll take this to
a
vote now.
Um
who all in favor of leaving this as
whole mushroom fruing bodies only?
Uh raise your hands please.
At present we have eight hands raised.
Okay, please lower your hands
and
after I see them all down, we'll go
ahead and
allow people to vote against. All
opposed to limiting this to whole
mushroom fruiting bodies, please raise
your hands.
uh present. We have four hands raised.
>> All right. With that said, we'll go
ahead and um amend this document to show
that we've voted 8 to four for whole
mushroom fruing bodies to be used for
this program.
All right. So, the next part here, let's
go into So, I just had a couple concerns
on this part, like
as I was kind of going back through this
document, c
um some of these seemed excessive,
right? So, we have cultivation and
harvest. Obviously, if you're going to
cultivate, you're going to harvest.
Packaging is going to happen both after
cultivation and harvest and and after
processing, I assume. So, I think we
should remove uh those two and just
permit cultivation and processing.
Is there any comments around this?
>> M your hand is raised and your mic is
enabled. Please begin.
Seems the hand was lowered. Uh so uh
Dominic, oh actually no, we have another
hand raised there. Um by a phone number
I believe it might be might be someone.
Do you want to go ahead?
>> That the phone number should be Matthew.
Let him go ahead. Uh first
>> absolutely uh to unmute it is uh star
six I believe
>> hello.
>> There we go. Matthew, we can hear you
now.
>> I'm sorry for all these technical
difficulties.
Um, so just to go back on the permits
real quick, I just wanted I had some
time to review this and I was thinking
um for the micologist that is a hobby
micologist and for the different types
of ways for all people to have access. I
was thinking about how about different
so like a micro tier, maybe a community
tier and like a commercialized tier. So
that way we can have paths and avenues
for the home micologist to enter.
What do you think about that Chris?
We're a micro business even.
>> So
>> I'm sorry. Can
>> I actually can answer that if if that's
okay. So, so Matthew, the the issue is
is that it has to be within the medical
program. And so we're not limiting how
much individual organizations would need
to grow or individuals to grow, but it
would have to be a part of the medical
program. It could not be separate as a
uh you know just an individual who wants
to grow and consume. It has to be a part
of the program. So someone would have to
apply for a permit to be a part of this
program.
Uh yeah,
this like looking at the um equitable
access that the domestic cannabis
program had was the the ultimate license
was kind of what what killed it. At
first it was designed to make it there
was no monopolies and everybody could
have access to it, but um capital and
real estate compliances, it resulted in
a a harder way. So for me, I'm I'm
worried about this happening again. Big
companies are going to come in. They're
going to push out all the little guys.
So I was trying to That doesn't mean
that their medicines are any better
because they're mass-produced. And dare
I say the stewardship of the small
batches makes them more valuable. So
even if we were in the scope of the
medical program itself, how would we go
about including some of these guys that
are on this call now who
is self-taught micologists who could
help us spread psilocybin and make
people better? How do we add them? And
that's why I was thinking of this tier
system.
>> Sure. And I completely understand that,
Matthew. I can tell you what really
happens with regard to when you separate
it out into the micro business sort of
realm is uh a lot of that had to do with
fee structure. There actually are no
fees with regard to this particular
program as far as uh the department of
health aspect of it. There may be other
fees for other you know permits uh
inspections for example from you know
for your certificates of occupancy that
sort of thing but the program itself is
not going to have those. Um and um and
that's a part of where that access sort
of comes in. And what has actually
happened continually with regard to
cannabis as the micro businesses were
created is they continue to ask can we
get more plants? Can our limit be
increased? And so it actually creates
sort of a false uh in many ways a false
dichotomy between the larger businesses
and the smaller ones. Um and so
completely understanding the access that
is a part of where some of [snorts] the
potentials with regard to equity and
access we'll need to address but um by
actually limiting or by trying to create
a separate classification
uh actually creates additional problems
and inhibits that because anybody who is
involved in this program as far as for
cultivation um has to be permitted and
licensed and that process is not really
going to be any different um in able to
do that uh because it's still going to
have the same safety issues, the same
testing issues, all of those sort of
things. It's not something that can be
sold to somebody uh out of a dispensary
type situation. It has to be uh
administered within the therapeutic um
approved locations. And so that is one
of the big issues with regard to that.
So understanding that yes we need to
ensure that there's that access but
trying to separate out a lensure uh I
mean there's not very much that we'd be
able to do of saying well we'll reduce
fees well half of zero fee is still zero
so uh you know and that was one of the
big issues with regard to cannabis is
the fees per plant were very large um
and that was part of the problem and why
micro businesses were proposed
originally but uh unfortunately as we've
already seen with that they've requested
increases and it's exactly for the
reasons you were stating that uh without
those increases they cannot continue to
compete with those other larger
operations and so they need to be able
to change that in order to be able to
still be successful and survive.
Thank you very much for that Gregory.
Your hand is raised just a moment though
that I was just responding to that
question. The main reason I had actually
put my hand up initially was one of the
questions that we had and why harvest is
actually on here is because under
current law you can actually grow
psilocybin legally in New Mexico, but
you cannot harvest and use it. And so
the question on why it was there is will
we want to have that there as a
potential safety mechanism for the
producers? Now remember there's not a
fee for this. So what we envision from a
standpoint of the application is that
those individuals who are doing this
will simply check off on what different
areas uh that they want the permitting
for. And so then they would be able to
have that. It would be one process. So
it's not like they would actually have
to submit separate applications for
each. they would simply just apply an
click a box to in the application to be
able to say yes, we want to do this. And
so the idea behind having that harvest
was to help provide a little extra
protection potentially. It may not be
necessary, but that was part of the idea
behind it. And then the idea on the
packaging is because we do envision down
the road where it may also be a
situation as the program grows and as
we're not just having uh small amounts
of psilocybin produced but larger
amounts that it may be something that um
the packaging may be outsourced and so
there may be a different organization
that is actually doing the packaging.
For example, if it's being put into pill
form, something like that, where that
equipment may be very expensive for an
individual operator to purchase, but a
manufacturer who's doing packaging may
be able to do that and do that across
other organizations that are doing
cultivation and thereby help reduce the
cost. So again, that was part of the
idea behind inclusion of that. Again, as
we've said before, this is not the end-
all beall at this point and even the
first set of rules will not be. So, that
could be something that we consider down
the road if it is removed or it could be
left in and again the individuals and
the organizations that are applying for
the cultivation simply check all of the
boxes for those things they want to do.
But that was the idea behind this
looking to the future quite frankly on
that. So, that's just those ideas and
I'm going to be quiet now because really
we do want to hear what people uh have
to say regarding it.
>> Thank you for that, Dominic. Uh Gregory
Evans, your mic is enabled. Please,
>> Dominic, I think we all benefit every
time you speak. So, um I mean I don't
know if you need a little pat on the
back, but you're doing a good job.
>> Um thank you.
>> Um yeah, I mean that's why I'm here.
um to address Matthew's question, I
think I really understand where you're
coming from, but I think um
zeroing in on the like the ninja level
context that we're like driving into
where this is going to be a very
sharp blade of an action. We are going
to create a very specific opening of the
ability to like normalize this through
this medical context. And so like the
regulations around a facility, you know,
which we're coming to cl Chris, like
those will define who can and can't
because like I can't afford rent to this
place where I am going to produce like
medical grade psilocybin mushrooms. I'm
not going to do that. I don't want to do
that. I will continue as a law-abiding
citizen to culture my psyllium in my
home, grow it on substrate, and not
harvest it.
I will continue to do that um within
it's not exactly like the confines of
the laws, but it's it's inside like the
the what do they call it? The there is
uh
my words aren't working today,
everybody.
>> Precedent. Thank you.
So, as far as like individuals being
stewards of this medicine, I don't think
that that's necessarily going to change.
Um, and I'm not recommending that
anything happen that's outside of the
explicit confines of the law moving
forward. But what we need to do is be
really careful how we talk about this
stuff and how we move forward in support
of the medical system because that
medical system is going to open a door
to normalization that if we're as we're
patient and as we support this entire
organism, we will see growth happen that
allows for um different levels and
different types like down the line. I'm
the kind of person that would produce a
boutique
unique species that nobody else grows
that's like,
you know, some thing that nobody's ever
heard of that has very unique qualities
and I'm going to make enough for five
people and not for a mass market. But we
also have to consider as we move into
this first iteration of of the industry,
we're not going to there is not going to
be a lot of production. There is not
going to be a lot of sales. Colorado
still hasn't really sold more than like
a pound. Like somebody has metrics on
that somewhere, but like there have not
been sales. Like people are producing
pounds and destroying them because they
can't have more than x amount in their
facilities.
So um as we start up, I think slow and
slow, I don't see more room like I think
one or two producers is going to have be
sitting on
excess product in the first year.
That's just a fact. Like we're going to
have to have enough for the people. But
then also like the idea that we're not
constrained to to to only holding one
license. I think that there will be
partnership sort of things that pop up
in the market and this is speculation
where a smallcale producer and a
facilitator partner with their licenses
and do a little vertical integration.
We don't know how this stuff is going to
manifest but we but as we write the
language we can kind of sculpt like what
we think is going to be safe and best
for patients and best for the
perspectives the perspective of how this
program is perceived not not nationally
but like internationally like this is
literally going to change the world.
>> Thank you for that. Next Dan Houston.
Dan your mic is enabled so please do go
ahead.
>> Okay. Yeah. So uh on the uh different
licenses the cultivator harvest
processing packaging uh I agree harvest
should be gone packaging should be gone
and under processing
um that needs to have two different
options for endorsements.
Um, and it shouldn't cost any more to
have one or both, but you should have a
uh edible manufacturing under the
processing and then uh um concentrate
under the processing is what is what I
see the processing license is. So under
the processing you can either process it
into concentrates or process into
edibles but and edibles require more of
the FDA whatever's you know kitchen and
all of that versus processing you into
concentrates.
Um and then uh the keypad entry um
that's a little excessive. I think it
should just say something about a
commercial grade lock or equivalent and
people should be allowed to use keypads
if they want but or just normal everyday
locks. Um I use keypads everywhere
because fingerprint everywhere because
um people don't lose their their key and
um it's really easy to disable
somebody's fingerprint. But that's just
me. Um I put up in the in the chat some
numbers. um one grower can grow for the
entire state of New Mexico uh without a
problem. What we got going on here in
Oregon currently
uh currently here in Oregon um we have
growers that grow a little bit and then
suspend their license for a while and
then they reactivate their license and
grow a little bit more and suspend their
license um in order to extend the amount
of time they have their license for. and
to um and and they all understand that
they they there there's too many
manufacturers here in Oregon and nobody
is moving the product that they thought.
So having altered tiers or whatever it
doesn't I mean one grower can grow for
all Mexico New Mexico. So do you need
multiple tiers? Um I would say no. Uh, I
put in the chat though some volumes that
have been moved here in Oregon. And you
see we have a decrease. We probably have
a decrease because of Colorado coming on
board. But also there are um illegal
edibles out there on the market.
Somebody mentioned the chocolate bars
and head shops are uh good because
everybody's coming on board, but they're
not. It has prescription medication and
all kinds of stuff that we found in it.
We have a paper published in the Journal
of American Medical Association. I
posted that. But take a look at some of
these numbers, guys. Um it's not going
to be a big program. Keep it simple.
Yeah. And and thank you for that, Dan.
And the numbers especially. And just as
a note again, as we kind of said before,
is it's going to be a homogenized
product. It so there's not going to be
concentrates or edibles in the initial
stages of the program. That is something
that can be determined and potentially
added down the road. And some of it has
to do with some of the additional
lensure and the other organizations or
or uh the other agencies that would need
to be involved. Um but again initially
the initial aspects is going to be the
homog homogenized product.
>> Oh so what is the processing for then?
What's that license for?
>> That again is because we do have to set
it separately and in the event that we
do have different cultivators who join
together. So for example, as Matthew was
saying, you may have some small
cultivators who are joining together,
may not have the equipment for doing
that processing and the packaging and
all of that. And so then they could
potentially do that through another
lency.
>> And that's the idea for having those as
separate.
>> And again, it's not a whole separate
application. It's just simply those who
are interested in doing those aspects
complete those portions, click on it.
It's We're going to make sure that
that's as simple as possible.
>> I hope that helps.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Sorry, I was I I took processing
because we have processing out here.
People make edibles and they make uh
concentrates. Nobody's really doing the
consuming the concentrates, but they
took they they put the concentrates into
the edibles. I really believe that you
guys need to allow edibles 100%. I'm
sorry. I'm a probably a little late to
the game on that one, but you need
edibles.
>> Thank you, Dan.
>> Thank you, Dan. Um, we have Estan hand
up. Um, your mic is enabled. Please
begin when ready.
>> Hey, I'll keep this very brief. I just
wanted to offer some insight on uh state
of New Mexico Pratt, which is often the
precedent people are citing when it
comes to growing psilocybin in New
Mexico. Uh, I actually have done a lot
of research on this because I was uh
famously uh interviewed in a gotcha
style journalism by the quote unquote
journalist at KOB TV uh claiming that I
said growing mushrooms are legal in New
Mexico. So the real outcome of uh that
particular Supreme Court case court case
was that uh by Pratt producing
psilocybin mushrooms in a home
environment, he was not guilty of
trafficking by manufacturer. That being
said, he still could have been legally
charged with possession or possession
with intent to distribute. So, an
important thing to keep in mind, it is
not currently legal to grow mushrooms in
New Mexico. It is just not considered uh
trafficking by manufacturing.
>> Thank you for that. Next, we have uh
James Brown. James, your mic is enabled.
>> Hey, Chris and everyone. I just uh I
wanted to echo Dan's stuff on
simplicity. Um and you guys keep saying
it. I I just think that some of these as
we clean this up a little bit. Um like
the keypad entry, I don't think it's
needed. Um and like Dan said with some
of the other ones, I think we could
skirt those off or combine them into
two. Um and then I, you know, I wanted
to also bring up that other comment I
put it in the chat about live agar and
you know, live cultures in Agar, what
what is there anything that we need to
do with that? Is that part of the
biomass or is that something that falls?
Do we need to talk about that at all?
>> I think we'll get to that
>> um that part of it.
>> Um
>> did you have something Dominic? Yeah, I
was just going to say as we've kind of
talked about before is, you know, as we
go through these and and realize we've
put these in here a lot because it's
been feedback, conversation, other
items. It doesn't necessarily mean it's
a stance of the department, for example,
to have that. Obviously, as we're going
through, I'm letting everyone know
here's what we think we need to do as
far as for getting the program started
initially. Doesn't mean that things
won't get added in. Um, and sort of some
of the ideas. So, please do not worry
about you're not going to hurt feelings
or any of that. But as far as for uh
doing that with regard to the liquid um
and the agar, uh I don't actually think
we need to because that is getting into
the nitty-gritty of telling the
cultivators this is how you grow, how
you don't grow, what you can, can't use.
So, I don't think that we need to, as
we've kind of said with some of the
other items, like for example, which
species to use. And so I think if we're
keeping that in mind as we go through
these, taking some of those things out
or not even adding them in is actually
kind of the way to go if that makes
sense. But it's a great question. I'm
glad you brought it up.
I hope that helps.
Fantastic. We have a hand up by Gregory
Evans.
Gregory, your mic is enabled.
Um, I had something to say. I think
we're good though. Like I mean I think
you said everything, Dominic.
>> Excellent. All right. So, um, you know,
I'm satisfied with Dominic's experience
rolling out the marijuana program to
keep the harvesting and packaging in the
permitting process, especially since
there isn't going to be a charge and
it'll be essentially a click box saying
I want a permit for XYZ. And um but if
anybody wants to challenge that and push
for a vote, I am about the democratic
process. So if you would like a vote on
that portion of it, please raise your
hand.
Okay, we'll go ahead and keep that part
in. And then I did hear a great
recommendation from Dan about uh adding
commercialrade locks to the keypad entry
or to the to the uh
next portion here.
And just so everybody knows and Chris
and everybody that's here is these are
just some examples. Um it basically uh
as a part of the the rules it would be
that the um the organizations would have
to uh basically just provide us a plan.
It's not necessarily that because
different locations are going to have
different um ne needs and um from a
security standpoint. So we don't want to
get into again the nitty-gritty. So
these are really just for example and
maybe the way we should do it is it
should be IE double locks security
system surveillance commercial grade
locks that sort of thing and again that
dependent upon the location is going to
depend exactly how secure and what
additional security features they may
need.
>> Okay. So, is that going to be part of
like a an inspection saying your
security is good enough for this
location given?
>> Yeah, they would have to basically
present a plan. So, that's the
demonstrate that the products are kept
secure. Um, and so how they would do
that is just basically what they would
need to do. And so, we just have these
are here as some examples of ways that
things can be secured.
>> Okay. Okay. There's that. And by the
way, it doesn't include because it we
did have a discussion about it. Um, but
because it is Friday afternoon, I'm
going to tell everybody we did talk
about the fact that every cultivator
should have sharks with lasers strapped
to their heads for security purposes.
So,
>> Greg, do you have another comment?
Yeah, I think just a real world scenario
just for perspective, it's like you go
to this website, you say, "I want a
thing."
A [clears throat] compliance officer
responds to that and says, "Hey, show me
your plan. There's a form that will be
created way down the line by well, maybe
in less than six months
somewhere somewhere here. There will be
a form created that just says here fill
this out and then the compliance
body from the from the regulating
department then comes looks at the thing
and says cool you are in compliance
please proceed signs a piece of paper
and then maybe has some cadence of of
checks. Um, and I think what Dominic was
saying here is like the the bullet point
is what's important. The specifics
um are less. But I think the more gr
like the less granular those are like
the categories of types of ways that we
can make things safe. Sharks. Was that
lasers?
>> Yes. With lasers strapped to their
heads. For those who don't get the
reference, you know, uh, it's a movie.
just [laughter]
um my biggest concern is Gira.
>> But yeah, um let's try to get through
this. Um yeah, I'm here.
Okay.
All right. So, I I think I I I'm
grabbing that or I'm picking that part
up now. Uh, and I think what we got
there is good enough.
Um, so the next thing I saw, and I just
I'm kind of dropping down to the notes
that I uh noticed. So, if other people
have reviewed this document and have
noticed something that they think we
should challenge or change or vote on, I
I'd appreciate
uh you speaking up or raising a hand and
that way we can um make this as best as
we can. Uh I saved this bullet point
here for a sunset clause which I believe
um we're going to have somebody
introduce language for next session
hopefully.
Yes. And Chris, just to note, I realized
that we had it on our other checklist,
but I didn't include it on here, so I
just added it. And it's the registration
with New Mexico tax and revenue.
>> Um, and are there any other se questions
about section B here?
>> And just really quick, oh, I'm sorry. I
did not put I think I may have missed
putting the last section into the chat
as I was doing with the first few. My
apologies if I did. So, but I'm going to
put that this one here so people have
it.
And a lot of this doesn't look like it's
going to be very negotiable, right? Like
this is just how do you have to kind of
operate if you're a business within New
Mexico,
>> right?
>> Yeah.
And oh before we go to Estabana I just
Zach I just want to um uh just note is
you do have a question about the entire
facility should not require you are
correct. If you notice the language
there says it's demonstrate that the
mushrooms and products are kept in
secure location. So if you have an
office or something like that it doesn't
necessarily need that same level.
Although I think most of the time it
will because they're usually contained
in a building, but again there could be
differences there. But thank you for
that. That's an important point.
Okay. And sorry, Estabon.
>> Yeah, thank you. Um yeah, I just have a
question regarding um the uh
authorization from uh landlords or
building owners. Um I see that that's
listed as a requirement to get the
license and I'm wondering if that's sort
of a chicken and egg scenario. I feel
like a lot of uh commercial real estate
owners, if you were to present them with
the idea of, hey, I'd like paperwork
documenting that I can grow what is a
federally regulated and illegal
substance here for the state, oftentimes
they're going to ask, well, let's see
proof from the state that you're even
qualified to do this. Do you face any
similar issues with the cannabis
program?
>> Uh, we did actually experience that. And
in fact, some of what happened in the
early parts of the program, and it has
happened at least a couple times, I'm
aware of since, is where um people would
submit their application and then they
were not able to move forward because
when the landlord found out what was
going on and what they were going to do,
they pulled their contract. So people
had invested a lot of money into doing
uh and and setting up for their license
and then ended up actually on the back
end of it so to speak where they weren't
even able to start up. Um and so that's
actually a part of it and why that proof
is really um required in the beginning
because we don't want to set people up
for failure. Yes, it does create on the
other side exactly what you're saying,
but in many ways it's better to find
that out in advance than to suddenly
invest a lot of money into something and
then suddenly have the rug pulled out
from under you.
>> That makes sense. So, could applicants
reach out for say, you know, whatever
the equivalent of a letter
recommendation would be from the state
essentially saying, "Yes, this person is
applying for the program under legal
purview."
>> Yes. And we actually used to do that
with cannabis as well.
Wonderful. Thank you.
>> I don't know if they're doing that
currently, but we did used to.
[laughter]
>> Thanks.
>> Is that Is that something we need to add
language in here for, Dominic, or is
that something that's going to be taken
care of in the wash?
>> That that doesn't need to be in
regulation. That's just something that
the program does. So, it doesn't have to
be regulated.
>> Okay. Okay. Excellent. Essentially what
it is is it says um what the letter B
essentially is is it's just saying that
that individual or that organization is
going through the process for an
application.
>> Excellent.
>> Gregory, your hand is raised.
Uh your mic is enabled.
>> If this isn't the right place, just let
me know. Um I had this [clears throat]
whole
brainworm about
uh speed to market and had this whole
thing that I haven't sent in because
it's not quite finished writing, but
like the idea that like is it going to
behoove us to license existing
agriculture farms to like so to to
leverage existing
infrastructure in the market in an
effort to help us move forward more
quickly like um what as Estavon, you
have a farm or whatever. It's like do
you get that like is there a risk in and
having that dual lensure with your food
and whatever? Um, and I like like adding
that like confirmation for the lensure
with the land owner or whatever like and
maybe maybe this is like a conversation
for a different spot or a different day,
but like just trying to think of that
like how we can leverage to meet the
needs of the
accelerated deadlines
>> or more of just question.
>> Thank you for that. We have Shane
McDaniel as well who wishes to uh make a
comment. Your mic is enabled, Shane.
>> Yeah, just a question. Are we going to
expedite
cultivators and testing ahead of some of
the other practitioners
so that we can have product to um set up
and establish testing procedures
so that that isn't uh you know all done
at the same time. And then the people
that are going to be providing um
medicine to the end user to the c to the
patients don't have to wait
3 months after everything else gets
started up to start getting product or
so basically are we going to put some
sort of
limited amount number of cultivators to
come up with the first round of product.
>> Yeah. So Shane, that's actually why we
have prioritized these particular
regulations for the cultivation and
testing so that we can get that. We
heard very clearly from many of the
folks from both Colorado and from Oregon
that we really needed to have product
before we even have patients because we
also need it with regard to some of the
training potentially and in some other
areas as well for testing or not other
areas but also for testing to ensure
potency and things like that. And since
it takes time to grow that's why we're
prioritizing this. Our hope is that we
have these regulations or our plan, it's
not a hope, it's our plan is that we
have these regulations uh complete and
ready and that we'll be able to do the
applications this summer so that um the
cultivators and the testing can actually
occur
uh before uh the uh the all of the um
the trainings are occurring and before
everybody is starting as a patient in
December uh of 26. So yes, that is a
part of it. As we kind of mentioned
during uh the board meeting, I believe
it was, it may have been one of the
other committees. My apologies. We've
had so many meetings, they've run
together a little bit, but what we had
talked about essentially is the priority
or the the the process is going to be
the um cultivating and testing, then the
lensure. So meaning the education and
the training needed for the various
levels of practitioners. Um and then at
that point the the final bit will be the
licensing for the actual locations. Now
it doesn't mean that we're not working
on those pro those processes. That's
just the priority. And in fact to help
us with regard to uh because we have
such a small staff. uh in order to make
sure that we're doing the cultivating,
we've actually been asking the other
committees to hold off on meeting till
after the legislative session and simply
so that we can focus on this aspect and
it's a part of why this committee as we
mentioned last time is actually meeting
so often right now so that we can
actually get through these processes and
create the regulations for them. So I
hope that helps with regard to that. But
yes, we are actually doing that as fast
as we can.
>> Thank you.
Excellent. Um,
I was just looking in the chat about
some of the this stuff. I I think we
considered MGAP
um as being a recommendation before and
we've kind of u denied the need to make
that into regulation. uh we're going to
let the the market sort that out and
then as Dominic said, we're working as
fast as we can to get the licensing up
and then people can apply for licensing
and the credentials will shake out in
this
regulation that we're setting up right
now. So,
um okay,
which brings me to the next part, which
is zoning and municipal permits.
uh
you know, you're not going to be able to
grow medicinals psilocybin mushrooms in
your closet um for this program.
Matthew, do you have a comment?
Matthew, you may have to unmute from
your phone. We can't hear you. Yeah.
Yeah, just a quick question. Just a
quick question. Uh,
>> so for those that of us that live in
rural areas and have exterior buildings
and such, what I'm worried about is um
not about zoning. So, agriculture
zoning, commercial zoning, it's all it's
all different in rural areas and not
just about that. I'm worried about are
my local government even even
participating in the program at all
because there's a lot of stereotypes
that go with magic mushrooms especially
you get out here on the east of New
Mexico um closest to Texas all very
biblical even if we're trying to teach
them it's for hospice care and for
addictions and the plethora of stuff
that it can do. [snorts] So, this is a
big concern for me. Um, the zoning in
general and how it's set up. And I just
I understand that we don't want people
growing shoe boxes of mushrooms in their
closet, but I also am worried about
local government
getting it not allowing it to get going
before it can based on zoning issues.
They can basically manipulate this
verbiage to make it say whatever it
wants to. So, if it could be a little
bit more open-ended, I would I would
appreciate that.
>> Dominic, do you want to tackle this one?
>> Yeah. Uh, so so thank you, Matthew, and
completely understand that. You know,
there have been some issues with regard
to that regarding cannabis. Um, the
statute does not actually allow us to
override um that the local zoning and
that's why we actually do have the note
here about local governments. So that is
something that uh currently is there. Um
and um uh unfortunately that's not
something that we can overrule as an
executive agency through our rulem. Um
so we do have to go forward with that
but we want to make sure that people
know that that is something that they
need to look at as far before they
decide to start on this kind of an
endeavor. And that's why we have that
specifically as a note.
So, but completely understand what
you're saying on that.
Um, and then just while I'm just
talking, Zach, the the food safety
training does not actually require a
food permit or food permit from the
state or local government. Um, it's just
one of those where uh there are several
standardized trainings here in New
Mexico. And so that makes it a little
easier to ensure that people are getting
the training without actually having to
turn around and write up their own uh
educational requirement for that. And
that's part of why we included that on
in there.
And sorry for those who aren't reading
the chat. Zach just had a question about
removing the food safety training if it
requires a food permit from state or
local government. And just the answer is
it doesn't require that.
Okay. If there's no further comment on
C or D,
um we're in section what, three right
now? Is would [clears throat] anybody
like to
um push a vote for section three to kind
of be
uh accepted?
Chris Chris, I would actually ask from
the department standpoint that we leave
it as it is right now until the next
meeting. Um because I think there's
still some conversations to be had. Some
people still have some thoughts and I
don't want to squaltch that because this
is so important and for example, we
still have the the um sunset clause to
determine and a few other things
especially for example here in section
D. So I would say let's let people you
know consider it think about it a little
bit more um since our next meeting is
next Wednesday that it's not a lot of
time but it gives some time for people
to consider and think about it because
the other part is there are things that
we may not have thought about right now
as we're reading through it and uh we'd
like to make sure that people do
consider it. uh you never know people
come up with ideas that nobody else has
thought about it and uh that we can then
turn around and suddenly that light bulb
moment happens and we want to be able to
allow that as much as possible. So I
would just say to hold off on voting on
it at the moment until then
if that helps.
>> Yes. Thank you Dominic. Feel free. I
want to extend that invitation to
anybody else. If somebody feels like
we're moving too fast on something and
they need time to consider it, please
let me know. And you know, we do have a
deadline coming up, but also we don't
have to get everything figured out for
that. So, we can always come back to
something um if we need more time on it.
So, please speak up if you feel like
we're moving too fast on something. I
appreciate it.
>> [clears throat]
>> And there is a question uh from James
about is quantity and inventory part of
this document. James, could you expand
on that a little bit? Do you mean are we
putting inventory limits on it? If so,
no, we are not. Um, so if that's it, but
if you mean something else, could you
explain it a little bit more?
Uh, that was it. Okay. Yeah, there we're
not putting an upper limit on that.
Thank you.
We're just not sure how much the sharks
with the laser strapped to their head
can actually protect. So,
sorry everybody. It is the Friday
afternoon at the end of a a very busy
and good but long week. So, my apologies
if my humor is not uh appreciated. Um, I
get it, but I have to make myself laugh
a little bit here and there. [laughter]
I think Matthew, did you have another
comment?
>> Uh, yes sir. So just
>> Yes, sir.
>> So just to touch on that sunset idea you
had, Chris, what if you made it so New
Mexico residents only? So if you owned
any of these businesses, maybe you could
put in the law that you have to be a New
Mexico resident or you have to pay a
income tax return in New Mexico. Just
something softballing there.
>> I think that is the the general intent
there and I believe Estebon is is going
to be working on that for us. So
um hopefully that answers your question.
Okay, let's uh let's continue down to
another one here. Let's go into growth
mediums. So
um
right now under current
uh regulate or you know our framework
that we're working on here, we're not
restricting any
uh substrates. Okay. So
um but they all have to be documented,
tracked by batch, fully disclosed on
file product labeling. Is anybody have
any issue with that or have any comment?
And just as a little bit of explanation
in a very small bit is the reason for
the fully disclosed is as some of the
information we've gotten for example Dan
has provided from Oregon where people
have had reactions that sort of thing.
This way people are know that they can
you know what the products are or
potential contaminations with regard to
for example grain or corn or anything
like that.
>> Estan can uh you unmute and go ahead.
>> Um yeah I just had a couple questions
here. So uh tracking by batch. What are
we defining as batch on there? Um, is
this a single brick of cocoa choir or is
this an order of 10 pallets?
>> Yeah, we're we're gonna get there.
We and we that may be another one we
come back to. I I threw Colorado's
definition of batch in here. We'll talk
about that and see if that works for us.
Um, but if people are more than welcome
to bring different language on batch and
we can debate that. Um, but I would like
to
>> My mistake I thought by batch on there
it was referring to batch of substrate.
I see what you mean.
>> Yeah. So, I I think part of the
definition of a batch of mushrooms is
going to be that it all has to be grown
on one sub, you know, same substrate and
that way it can be documented throughout
the process what this batch of mushrooms
was grown on, the potency of it, and all
the other
all the other testing, labeling we're
going to do.
Does that
>> Okay, thank you. Um, yeah. Yeah, that
definitely answers that section of it.
Um, my other question was, uh, fully
disclosing substrate on there. Is this a
simple list of ingredients on there? Is
this abiding by the USDA's, um, uh,
allergen listing? You know, essentially,
are we listing this was produced in a
facility that also processes corn, or we
having to literally say, you know, corn
grain spawn was used, there's six
ingredients in our substrate, so on so
forth. Yeah, Estabbon. The idea behind
it is uh to actually have what is used
in that particular substrate.
>> Okay, thank you.
>> And and again, the main reason is just
so that individuals who have particular
allergies or other uh you know uh other
potential concerns about contaminants
can actually be able to uh you know know
what is in the product that they are
consuming.
And you will notice we don't have
specific language. We just want to
ensure it's fully disclosed.
>> Gregor, do you want to go ahead and go
next?
>> Um, I think we could add
maybe a caveat on the product labeling
to like like we're moving into a world
where like the idea of labeling is a
little bit closer to something that we
can research more deeply. So like having
language that says or a QR code, click
this and see the full description of
this thing, but like access to that
information. Maybe we could freephrase
that as like
the end user has full access to the
information for this purpose and maybe
call out specific warnings because it's
like it's going to get so confusing when
people start putting arythritol and like
different types of like azamite or
vermiculite and people are going to
start wondering what vermiculite is and
it's just it's it's messy on the label.
Maybe that's my
>> Greg. We're not to what the label itself
will actually look like yet. And we have
done in the past in other instances
where it is that here's what has to be
on the printed label. Here's the other
information that's available. So yeah,
we're just not to that point yet. So
don't worry about that.
>> Uh is what I would say. It's a good
point. We always want a label to be
readable for individuals who are looking
at it. Um, and so it may be more of
something like the final version be a
fact sheet, you know, um, for example,
like what you get when you go to a
pharmacy and pick up your
pharmaceuticals. You know, the label has
three or four items and then your fact
sheet has a thousand items listed. So,
>> I don't know if you ever bought
marijuana gummies, but those are real
hard to read, [laughter]
>> right? So we will be getting to that but
so don't worry about that as far as the
final aspects of labeling as far as how
that will look. We will make sure and
that it's accessible and yet um not
illeible. Yeah. Three point font. Right.
So [laughter]
>> um on batch I'm pasting in uh like a
draft
of what I was thinking. But when you're
talking I like and pause me immediately
if it's not the right time.
>> Yeah, I think batch is in the next set
of
>> Got it. Waiting
>> this
>> muting.
>> Okay, I think Zach, you're up next.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. I just wanted to tag on to the um
question about substrates and labeling
just to make sure that there wasn't
going to be any requirements for
tracking chain of custody from you know
cradle to grave. It's tracking and
labeling the ingredients or those
substrates within the actual facility.
>> Yeah. Thank you, Zach. I was actually
going to ask you what exactly you were
meaning by that. I was a little
confused, but now that you've said that,
I get what you mean. Yes, it's just
going to be what is in that substrate,
what's in that growth medium, not
necessarily that it came from, you know,
Zach's farm, you know, at Highway 56 and
then was transferred to Chris, you know,
and yeah, it is just going to be what
are the the primary ingredients, you
know, that or or composition rather of
that growth medium and substrate.
All right. If there's no more um comment
on growth medium, I I think everybody's
kind of in agreement. We keep it as open
and broad as possible. And so I don't
see any need for changes there. Stop me
if I'm wrong. But let's go on to
environmental controls.
I know we kind of talked about a lot of
this in the last
um in a last
meeting, but uh we'll we'll go ahead and
hit it one more time. I don't know is
this second bullet even necessary? like
uh we just viewed a a u went and visited
a mushroom farm recently and obviously
there's a lot of uh
intention that goes into keeping
mushrooms from getting contaminated. Um
but I so I'm not sure that this is
something that needs to be put in
regulation and if I'm wrong please let
me know.
Great.
I mean, I'm kind of on the fence with
you. It's like it's going to be market
regulated. Like, mushroom farms are the
cleanest things in the universe.
Like, it's so important to be clean just
to not ruin everything. Um,
Zach's comment about crosscontamination.
My only concern about cross
contamination would be um,
spore drift is like really the only
concern. And if you have multiple
cultivars and then you accidentally
like
have one growing where it's not supposed
to be or if you're in a mixeduse
facility that has growing lines mane
pipino and then in another room you have
cubensus and your cubensus spores out
and the vents push um spores into
another room like that kind of thing. As
far as the biocurity measures, I don't
think it hurts to leave it in, but I
mean it's it's going to be on the it's
going to be somewhere in the compliance
forms anyways. Somebody's going to
somebody's going to be like, "Are you
doing your thing?" Yeah, I'm doing my
thing.
That's how compliance sounds. I'm an
expert.
>> All right.
>> Thoughts? So, so Chris, I'm seeing in
the in the um comments it's people
saying no, don't really need the
biocurity. So, uh is there any objection
if we take it off?
No. Okay. So, there we go. Easy.
[laughter]
Okay. And Chris, I would just recommend
because uh we're now uh at just about
quarter till five. I would recommend at
this point I think we've gone through a
lot and I think the definition in the
conversation about batch is going to be
a little bit of a long one um and
conversation on that. So I would
recommend um perhaps waiting until the
meeting on Wednesday for the and
continuing at that point. Um
>> Sure. Can you just um maybe scroll down
and drop it in the chat so people can
>> copy it if they want to? And I think
they can't have access to this document,
right, Dominic?
>> Yeah, actually we sent it out in the
meeting invite. So for everybody who has
the meeting invite, if you had signed up
for the meeting in advance, we sent you
out an email separately that actually
has the document. If you um signed up
after we had sent that email out, it is
actually in the invite for the meeting
itself. So, you should see it there, but
I'm also going to put it here in the
chat in just a moment.
>> So, I would really appreciate if people
kind of read ahead for next one and
bring their comments um and concerns to
the next meeting. And if you have
alternate language, you know, having it
prepared would be um would be excellent.
Or if you just have recommended changes,
like I said, this was Colorado's
um definition of a batch. And so
that's kind of a good place to start I
think.
Um
so
um just a a quick question if I may,
Chris. Um Zach, you're saying can we add
fungicides and pesticides?
Where at that where
can we unmute Zach?
>> Okay, Zach, you should be able to un
>> Yeah, I was that in that in the section
above batches where it mentioned
pesticides. I was just going to suggest
that we add fungicides to that as well.
Yeah, that's actually that's a good
point. That's actually been was brought
up in the last meeting and it was
actually split. So, uh I'd actually like
to hear some from some of the
cultivators. What do you think? Should
it be no pesticides and no fungicides
utilized? Is that reasonable or is there
a reason for that?
Shane, it actually was going back and
forth.
Nobody.
>> I think Greg has his hand up. Do you
want to speak to something here, Greg?
>> I mean, I like that that conversation I
think I'd like to leave for another day.
Um,
I had a kind of separate question when
it's time.
>> Okay.
Yeah. See, and this was a part of it is
we had it back and forth last week where
it's remove it or leave it. Uh if it's a
question of would people be utilizing it
anyway, is it something we have to test
for if it's not there in this itself?
But Estvon uh you've got your hand up um
and as a cultivator, can you go ahead
speak on this?
Yeah. So, in regard to fungicides, uh,
that's mostly a non-starter as, you
know, fungicides would actively kill the
product that you're growing on there.
Um, with some minor exceptions, things
like hydrogen peroxide. I think a better
bet than, you know, flat out saying no
fungicides, no pesticides, is perhaps we
could as a group or maybe even a few
folks offline come up with a list of
what we could see as potentially harmful
substances that people may attempt to
use and just issue a banned substance
list. Things like glyphosates or
whatever you may consider. Sure.
Okay. So, for the moment, we'll leave
that as is and uh people think about
what uh is possible to be used. Um how
about this? Um uh other
I I hate to use the word chemicals, but
I guess that that's the only thing
coming to my brain in a moment. If
anyone has something different, uh I'd
appreciate it. but um other chemicals um
uh determined harmful
by the department.
That way if there are changes to the um
uh to that list uh as the board reviews
it and things like that that could be
adjusted. Would that be work? Okay. Oh,
and I'm sorry my for some reason my
screen stopped sharing. I didn't realize
that. I may have my apologies.
There we go. So uh what I did is
hopefully you all can see it again. I
just added here at the end the other
chemicals is determined harmful by the
department
but
go ahead because you were you mentioned
that. So as far as a list go right
ahead.
>> Oh my apologies. I still had my hand up.
Um I Oh go ahead.
>> Oh I was just going to say I still had
my hand up previously. Please by all
means Greg.
Okay. Um,
>> oh, I'm still waiting to talk about
something else. If you have something
about this, um, please go ahead.
[clears throat]
There's a comment from Zach asking if we
could stick to a banned substance list,
and I I kind of agree. Is there a reason
you chose that language specifically,
Dominic?
Uh, I was just saying chemicals because
it was what was coming to my brain and I
couldn't get it out. So, I'm fine with
um uh it would actually be substances.
So, other substances determined harmful
by the department.
>> I did throw in some language that might
trigger trigger another thought. I said
anything that can leave residual traces
in the product downstream or something
like that like
as opposed to a chemical cuz like I mean
I use isopropyl alcohol and that's a
very harsh chemical but it doesn't end
up in product.
>> Yeah, I think substance would probably
be a little better in this case. It's a
little broader. And again, it would be
determined to be harmful. And that
determined to be harmful could include
residual traces.
>> There you go. No cocaine for your
mushrooms.
>> Okay. So, we're uh getting short on
time, Greg. I think you wanted to make a
comment about something else. Um let's
keep it brief. We only have a few
minutes and we have a couple more people
that want to talk. Um, I just wanted to
see if there was a way that we could
distribute or if that glossery that I
submitted was in review or if could be
made available because in that there's a
lot of like spec language for
definitions that will very much that are
very much centered around like this
specific committee and I would love
people tearing that apart and
reworking it and finding ideas in it and
what and all of that. Is that something
that we can do?
>> Yeah, it's actually under review right
now, Greg. We've submitted it for review
and it does take a little bit of time
for that to occur. It's a part of why we
have those sort of those deadlines, but
it can take 5 to 10 business days. So,
uh, since I think we just got that on
Tuesday, was it Monday or Tuesday? Uh,
[snorts] please give it a little bit of
time.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Okay, cool. Um would it be
inappropriate to like share some of
those specific pieces with people in
this group to like inform the language
that we're defining next week around
batch and lot?
>> Yeah, hopefully we'll have everything up
here within the next couple business
days.
>> Oh, okay. Cool. Cool. Awesome. Yeah.
again. And and this is part just to let
everybody know anytime we get items
submitted and I know we've put it before
into the chat and as far as per
submission that if we're getting
hundreds of pages that means it's going
to delay in getting posted because we
have had situations in the past for
example where people sneak or leave
accidentally inappropriate language and
so it actually has to all be reviewed um
prior to getting posted and that can
delay posting if it's really long
documents. ments and I think I've
mentioned before in this particular
group but if I haven't my apologies
where we will get uh submissions that
are hundreds of pages and we have to go
through all of that before it can go up.
So we ask that it be targeted um and
that we not get large documents that
have that because otherwise we're not
going to be able to provide them in a
timely fashion to the committee because
they do all have to be reviewed. They
will eventually get posted but it can
take time. So, please remember that that
we want to keep things focused so that
we're able to review items um you know
for the committees and that the
committee can have it and the board
members can have it. Um but when we get
items that are hundreds of pages uh they
have to be fully reviewed and they have
to before they can actually be posted
because they are public. It is a public
site and public document. So we have to
watch out for it. So,
>> and sometimes, by the way, it's very
inadvertent.
>> So, don't think that we're thinking
people are doing it on purpose, course,
although that could happen.
>> In that document, there is citation
links to scientific papers and and
existing research. Is it like is it
better for you if I retain and and like
say I like write the glossery and then
submit?
>> I need you to come wrap it up, buddy.
>> Yeah.
>> Done. Okay. Just Yeah.
Um perhaps an email to answer all these
questions might be more pertinent or
>> well we've gotten it from several people
Chris that's why I just wanted to
mention about the lengthy documents so
you know just make sure to keep things
focused. Thank you everyone.
>> All right we have a couple more people's
comments here. Uh Dan
>> um so something to think about. Um, I've
struggled with this and my
recommendation was is to do uh random
testing with clients for stuff like
pesticides and metals and stuff like
that. As a lab, we have not really done
much in the um licensed market. Um, but
we've bought products off of store
shelves um medicinal ones and have found
metals and pesticides in those. So, um,
yeah, it it things like fly strips
hanging from people's ceilings just to
catch the flies will actually
contaminate stuff and we found that in
cannabis testing. So, um, rat bait
poisoning
um, can be tracked in andor whatever and
that actually we can't even use that
around our laboratory because it affects
our equipment. Just side note. Thanks.
Bye.
Thank you, Dan, and thank you for all
your uh insights and lessons learned
from up there in Oregon. Um really
appreciate your time today.
Um Shane,
yeah, just quickly um on contaminants
and that kind of stuff, if we're going
to ban them,
um how are we going to are these things
we're going to have to test for? And if
we're going to be banning them and
testing for them, we need to make sure
that the lists match up, right? So, um,
you know, Dan could probably answer
better on that. I mean, if we're going
to say ban this particular fungicide,
and I'm just using that as an example,
but we can't test for that fungicide.
What's the use of banning it?
That's all. I'm just I'm just want to
make sure we're all we're all on the
same page there because I've seen that
happen before where things get banned
but it but since you can't test for it,
everybody continues using it,
>> right? And and that's a great point,
Shane. And yes, that is a part of one of
the things that we've been talking about
and thinking about.
Yeah, I I think um whatever testing
requirements we do too, I think the
Department of Health will always kind of
retain
authority to go in and do additional
testing as required and and we'll get to
that point in uh and hopefully our next
meeting which is going to be
on February 4th at from 3 to 5. The
meeting after that is going to be on
February 11th from 3:00 to 5:00. And um
I'd like to have or we need to have uh
initial recommendations and like I said
like me and Dominic have both said um
that doesn't mean we have to have
everything figured out but we're going
to submit initial recommendations from
this outline to the board after that
February 11th meeting. So,
um, yes, super grateful for everybody's
time and commitment to this process. And
Dominic, did you have any closing
thoughts?
>> Yeah, just the last thing is for the uh
public comments. We do need them to for
this record or this meeting record by uh
Monday uh at um 5:00 p.m. uh for us to
include it in this. If it's submitted
afterwards, it will can get included
later on, but I would recommend then
waiting until the after the next
meeting.
And other than that, thank you
everybody. Great discussions.
All right, we'll conclude the meeting
for today and um I can't wait to see you
all next Wednesday.
Thank you.
>> Thank you everyone.